Now that we've touched on and
explored some of the
different types of
risks in the futures and
broader financial markets,
let's now discuss
why the price of
a futures contract differs from
the price you might pay now.
The current market
settles on a spot basis,
which is typically for
immediate delivery,
where immediate
could mean two days.
Or for example, in a supermarket,
you would likely find
that the cash price
would equate to what
you would pay for,
say, corn at the cash register.
While shoppers can generally
buy corn throughout the year,
the crop might be harvested
just once annually.
It's the role of the
futures market to draw in
all known information
about next year's crop,
and figure out what the
forward or futures price is.
This is where producers, hedgers,
and speculators get together,
on a near 24-hour basis,
to assimilate the
latest information,
and reflect it through what
is called price discovery.
This is important information to
global financial and physical
market participants,
as futures allow them to see
the current price of a
product not yet produced.
The difference
between the cash or
spot price and the
forward or futures price,
is known as the basis.
If we take a look at the
prevailing market price
for the current corn contract,
for instance, and
compare it with, say,
the price of a futures contract
that expires in a year,
we can note the
difference between
these prices as the basis.
Changes in the basis deliver
their own message to producers.
Should forward prices
reflect too much supply of
a specific commodity at
a future date and time,
a farmer, for example,
might decide to switch
to a less abundant crop.
In our next video, we'll discuss
futures prices a bit further,
providing some insights
into concepts,
known as contango and
backwardation. Come
back and join us.